本期视频由Squarespace倾情赞助，助您轻松打造精美绝伦的网站
This video is sponsored by Squarespace, the easiest way to create a beautiful website.
回想起电影的早期峥嵘岁月，脑海中浮现的很可能是黑白影像
When you think of the early days of film, black and white images will likely come to mind,
银幕上的世界，全然由单色的灰阶描绘而成
with cinematic worlds exclusively portrayed in monochromatic shades of grey.
然而，特艺彩色（Technicolor）的到来，宛如一道色彩的闪光
But then, like a flash of colour itself, Technicolor arrived,
彻底革新了我们在大银幕上体验故事的方式
revolutionising the very way we experience storytelling on the big screen.
从《绿野仙踪》中郁郁葱葱，饱满的景色
From the lush, saturated landscapes of the Wizard of Oz,
到《红菱艳》里精致绝伦的色调
to the exquisite palettes in the red shoes,
它不再仅仅是一种工具，更成为了电影魔力的象征
it became more than just a tool, it became a symbol of cinematic magic.
让我们一同探寻特艺彩色的技术演进与历史轨迹
Let's explore the technical evolution and history of Technicolor,
看看这一开创性的工艺如何为画面注入生命
and look at how this groundbreaking process brought Hughes to life,
并永远地改变了电影制作
transforming filmmaking forever.
在二十世纪初，电影制作尚处萌芽阶段
At the start of the 1900s, when filmmaking was still in its infancy,
一些技术先驱，如爱德华·特纳
a few technical innovators, such as Edward Turner,
开始尝试制作35毫米的彩色胶片拷贝
began toying with the idea of creating a 35mm colour print.
然而，这些早期的实验可称得上凤毛麟角
However, these early experiments were few and far between,
直到1909年前后，首个主流的彩色电影摄影工艺
until around 1909, where the first major colour cinematography process,
一种名为Kinemacolor的技术，在英国应运而生
called Kinemacolor, was invented in Britain.
1915年其商业应用日渐式微后
After commercial use faded in 1915,
特艺彩色便接踵而至
it was followed by Technicolor.
但这项技术究竟是如何运作的呢？
But how exactly did this technology work?
特艺彩色试图以一种近乎魔幻的方式创造彩色影像
Technicolor sought to almost magically create a colour image,
同时利用的却是当时已有的黑白胶片
while using the black and white film which was available at the time.
其最初的迭代，被称为一号工艺（Process 1），采用的是双色系统
The first iteration, which was called Process 1, used a two colour system.
基本上就是将每一帧画面记录两次
Basically, it recorded each frame twice,
记录在同一卷35毫米黑白胶片上
on one roll of 35mm black and white film,
分别透过一片绿色滤镜和一片红色滤镜
behind a green filter, and a red filter.
该过程由一台特制的特艺彩色摄影机完成
This was done by a specialist Technicolor camera,
最初由沃尔瑟姆机械公司制造
which was initially manufactured by the Waltham Machine Company,
后来被主导早期摄影机制造业的米切尔公司接管
before it was taken over by Mitchell, who dominated early camera manufacturing.
为了能同时记录这两个影像
To record these two moving images at the same time,
这台特艺彩色摄影机使用了一个分光镜
this Technicolor camera used a beam splitter,
光线进入镜头后，被分流至两个区域
where light entered the lens, and was then diverted into two areas,
借助光学元件，通过不同的片门
through different gates, using optics.
这使得两个影像能被分别曝光
This allowed two images to be individually exposed to light,
并并列记录在同一条胶片上
and recorded next to each other on the same strip of film.
随后，胶片拷贝可通过一台带双镜头的特制放映机播放
Later, a film print could be played back by a special projector with two lenses.
其中一个镜头的光圈会产生红色调的影像
One with an aperture which created a red tinted image,
另一个则带着绿色的光圈
and the other with a green aperture.
当这两个不同色彩的影像被精确定位
When these two different coloured images were positioned correctly,
使它们在放映幕布上相互重叠
so that they overlapped each other on the projection screen,
便能产生活动影像的色彩雏形
they produced very rudimentary moving colour footage.
因为仅融合了两种颜色
Because just two colours were combined,
早期的特艺彩色只能呈现极为有限的色彩范围
early Technicolor could only produce a very limited range of colours.
他们选择了红色与绿色
They chose red and green,
因为他们想优先还原肤色与绿色的植物
because they wanted to prioritise skin tone colours, and greener foliage.
然而，这牺牲了捕捉其他色调的能力
However, at the expense of not capturing other hues,
例如蓝色或紫色
like blues or purples.
将这两个投射影像相结合的方式，被称为“加色法”
Combining these two projected images was called the additive colour process.
然而，它伴随着许多技术难题
However, it came with many technical glitches,
比如放映技师需要频繁地重新校准
such as the projector technician needing to very frequently recalibrate,
并调整放映机镜头的对齐位置
and reposition the alignment of the projector lenses.
这第一套工艺从未真正流行起来
This first process never really took off.
不过它促使特艺彩色重返绘图板，着手开发二号工艺
However, it did send Technicolor back to the drawing board to develop process number 2.
特艺彩色二号工艺没有改变双色摄影系统
Rather than changing the two colour camera system,
而是决定改进胶片的放映方式
Technicolor process 2 decided to alter how the film projection happened.
相较于第一套工艺的加色法
Instead of the first process's additive colour,
这项新工艺采用了减色法
this new process used subtractive colour.
这意味着它不再投射两个独立的红、绿影像
What this meant was that rather than projecting two separate red and green images,
减色法将它们合成为一个35毫米的彩色拷贝
subtractive colour combined them into one 35mm colour print,
可以直接通过普通放映机播放
which could be run through an ordinary projector.
经由特艺彩色摄影机，透过红、绿滤镜拍摄的35毫米黑白胶片
Once the 35mm black and white film rolls that were shot with a red and a green filter
一旦完成冲洗与印片
by the Technicolor camera were developed and printed,
它们就会被黏合在一起
they were stuck together,
然后在实验室中使用不同的染料进行染色
then colour toned in a lab using different dyes.
来自绿色通道的黑白胶片
The black and white film from the green side
会被赋予一种互补的，或者说相反的橘红色调
was given a complementary or opposite red-orange tint,
而来自红色通道的胶片，则会被染上青绿色调
while the film from the red side was given a green cyan tint.
当两者结合，便能生成一份基本的彩色拷贝
When combined, these produced a basic colour print,
可在电影院进行放映
which could be projected in cinemas.
尽管这极大地简化了放映流程
Although this vastly simplified the projection process
并提升了影院成片的质量控制
and increased the quality control of the product in cinemas,
它依然存在一些缺陷
it still came with a number of downsides.
其中一些问题在1928年更新的特艺彩色三号工艺中得到了解决
Some of these issues were addressed in the updated 1928 Technicolor Process 3,
它使得胶片拷贝更坚韧，更耐久
which made the print more hardy, durable,
不易刮伤，并且能在影院放映更长时间而不受损
less prone to scratching and able to play in cinemas for longer without getting damaged.
尽管技术已然精进
Despite the improvement in the technology,
特艺彩色公司仍未完全满足
Technicolor was still not entirely happy,
他们寻求发明一种全新的最终工艺
and sought to invent a new final process,
能够向观众呈现一个完整
which would be able to present a full,
饱满，且绚丽的色彩光谱
saturated spectrum of vivid colour to audiences.
在我们转向第四个，也是最终的特艺彩色工艺之前
Before we move on to the fourth and final Technicolor Process,
我需要感谢今天的赞助商，Squarespace
I need to thank today's sponsor, Squarespace.
广告空降7:04
双色工艺除了技术上的不足，其主要的缺憾在于美学层面
Apart from the technical downsides of the two colour process, the main negative was an aesthetic one.
仅用两种颜色来记录和染色胶片，严重限制了它能再现的色彩范围
Recording and toning film with only two colours severely limited the spectrum of colours it could reproduce.
为了克服这一点，他们决定将可记录的颜色从两种提升至三种
To overcome this, they decided to bump up the colours they could record from 2 to 3.
这需要与米切尔公司合作，制造一台全新的摄影机
This required manufacturing a whole new camera in collaboration with Mitchell.
当光线穿过镜头
Once the light passed through the lens,
它再次被分光镜在光学上分为两股不同的光束
it was again optically divided into two different streams by the beam splitter.
然而，这一次，不再是记录在一卷胶片上
However, this time, instead of recording to one roll of film,
每一帧画面被同时记录在三卷不同的35毫米黑白胶片上
each frame was recorded onto three different rolls of 35mm black and white film simultaneously.
一股光束被分离，穿过滤镜，使一卷胶片只对绿光曝光
One stream of light was split, passed through a filter and exposed one film roll to only green light.
另一股分离的光束首先被记录在一张正色片上
The other split beam was first recorded onto an orthochromatic film,
正色片是一种对波长580nm以下可见光感光的感光材料，其乳剂含有银盐和增感染料组成的化学涂层
感色范围覆盖380-580nm波段的蓝紫光至黄绿光
它只吸收蓝光
which absorbed only blue light,
然后再传递到第三张全色片上
before then passing to a third panchromatic film,
它只捕捉红光
which captured only red light.
这三卷黑白负片随后被送往实验室
These three rolls of black and white negative film were later sent to a lab
在那里它们被冲洗成黑白正片
where they were developed into a black and white positive,
然后，如同早前的减色法工艺
and then, like in the earlier subtractive colour process,
它们被染上位于色谱另一端的染料
they were toned with a dye that was on the opposite end of the colour spectrum.
于是，对红光曝光的黑白胶片被染上青色
So, the black and white film exposed to red light was given a cyan dye,
用蓝光记录的影像被染上黄色
the image recorded with blue light given a yellow dye,
而绿光影像则被染成品红色
and the green light image toned a magenta colour.
当这些青色，黄色和品红色的影像合而为一
When these cyan, yellow and magenta toned images were combined into one,
它们便能生成更为精确的色彩再现
they produced a much more accurate reproduction of colour,
更接近人眼所见的真实世界
closer to what the human eye sees.
能够捕捉到以往无法实现的色调
Being able to capture tones which before weren't possible,
比如蓝色以及介于其间的许多其他色彩
such as blues and many other colours in between.
这项三色工艺首次引人注目的应用
The first notable use of this three colour process,
淋漓尽致地展现其宽广的色彩捕捉能力
which showed off its broad range of colour capture,
是在迪士尼的动画短片《花与树》中
was on the Disney animated short, Flowers and Trees.
这种染料的组合创造出一种独特的特艺彩色质感
This combination of dyes created a unique technic colour look,
成为了从30年代初到50年代彩色电影的代表
that came to represent colour cinema from the early 30s to the 50s.
它拥有鲜明，浓郁，饱和的色彩
It had vivid, rich, saturated colours,
其中红色，橙色和黄色尤为醒目
with reds, oranges and yellows being particularly punchy,
而在明亮光线下，较浅的肤色则呈现出一种奶油般的古铜色柔和暖调
and brightly lit, paler skin tones having a creamy bronze pastel warmth.
这种增强的饱和度与对比度
This boosted saturation and contrast,
意味着较暗的阴影常常被压缩成纯黑
meant that darker shadows were often crushed to pure black,
并且缺乏细节
and lacked detail.
西装变成了一团没有纹理的深色块
Suits became dark blobs without texture.
这种色彩明亮而富有冲击力的特质
The bright punchy quality of this colour,
使其在好莱坞常被用于较为轻松愉快的类型片
meant it was often used in Hollywood for lighter entertaining genres,
例如歌舞片，动画片，冒险片或喜剧片
such as musicals, animation, adventure or comedies.
而黑白影像则常常为色调更暗，更具戏剧性的电影保留
While black and white was often preserved for darker, more dramatic films,
比如黑色电影类型
such as in the noir genre.
然而，也有某些电影制作人选择了特艺彩色
However, certain filmmakers did opt for technicolour,
为一些戏剧性的史诗巨制创造视觉奇观
to create a visual spectacle for some dramatic epics.
尽管这项三色工艺极大地改善了画面效果
Even though this three colour process vastly improved both the look,
以及早期工艺在放映上的局限
and the projection limitations of the earlier processes,
它也并非没有瑕疵
it wasn't without some flaws.
首先，使用这种三色特艺彩色工艺进行拍摄是昂贵的
Firstly, shooting in this three colour technicolour process was expensive.
由于需要三卷胶片
With their three film rolls,
它们使用的35毫米胶片量至少是黑白电影拍摄的三倍
they used at least triple the amount of 35mm film, compared to movies shot in black and white.
此外，这项工艺需要实验室进行更复杂的处理工作
Additionally, this process required more complex processing work in the lab,
来冲洗胶片并制作彩色放映拷贝
to develop the film and to make the colour projection print.
电影制片厂也无法购买自己的三色米切尔摄影机
Film studios also couldn't buy their own three colour Mitchell cameras,
只得从特艺彩色公司租用
but were instead forced to rent them from technicolour,
同时还要雇用他们的一位摄影技师和色彩总监
along with one of their camera technicians and colour supervisors,
他们要确保镜头前的服装和布景色彩
who made sure that the hues of the costumes and sets in front of the camera,
不会超出摄影机的能力极限
didn't push the camera's limitations.
因此，特艺彩色通常只为高预算的电影保留
Technicolour was therefore often reserved for higher budget films.
或者偶尔只用于几个特定的重要场景
Or occasionally only used for a few select set pieces,
而电影的其余部分则用黑白拍摄
with the rest of the movie shot in black and white.
除了成本，电影摄影师和剧组人员也面临挑战
Apart from the cast, cinematographers and crews were also challenged.
由于有一套分离光束的棱镜系统
Due to the prism system that split the light beam,
以及当时黑白胶片感光速度较低
along with the low speeds of the black and white film stock of the time,
他们不得不将胶片的感光度定得极低
they had to rate the film incredibly low,
大约仅为5 ASA
at around a mere 5 ASA.
ASA感光度是由美国标准协会（American Standards Association，ASA）制定的感光材料标准
这需要巨量的光线
This required an enormous amount of light,
尤其是在为大型布景打光时
especially when lighting large sets.
这种光通常来自碳弧灯
This light usually came from carbon arc sources,
其运行时温度极高，甚至会冒烟
which ran so hot that they would smoke,
将片场的温度提升到酷热的程度
raising the temperature's onsets to extreme heights.
另一个实际的缺点是声音
Another practical downside was sound.
当35毫米胶片在摄影机中运转时
When 35mm film runs through a camera,
会发出嗡嗡的声响
it makes a whirring sound.
由于三倍的胶片量通过摄影机
Having three times the amount of film passed through the camera,
搞得这些摄影机非常嘈杂
made these cameras very noisy.
以至于无法用它们录制同期声
So much so that you couldn't record sync sound with them,
除非使用所谓的隔音罩
without using what was called a blimp,
一种能减弱摄影机噪音的罩子
a cover that dampens the camera noise.
用于这些特艺彩色米切尔摄影机的隔音罩大得离谱
The blimps for these Technicolor Mitchell cameras were outrageously big,
使得移动这个沉重的庞然大物
and made moving this heavy hunk of machinery around
比使用标准的米切尔摄影机要困难得多
much more difficult than with a standard Mitchell camera.
三色特艺彩色从30年代初到50年代中期，有过一段辉煌的历程
Three color Technicolor had a great run from the early 30s to the mid 50s,
拍摄了许多经典的好莱坞电影
shooting many iconic Hollywood films.
然而，特艺彩色的落寞是柯达公司造成的
However, the death of Technicolor was inflicted by Kodak
50年代早期
in the early 50s,
随着35毫米电影彩色负片的问世
with the invention of 35mm motion picture color negative film.
这种伊士曼彩色负片，或ECN胶片工艺
This Eastman color negative, or ECN film process,
意味着不再需要庞大的摄影机
meant that instead of needing an enormous camera,
三卷黑白胶片
three rolls of black and white film,
和复杂的实验室染色过程
and a complex laboratory dyeing process,
你所需要的只是一台随便什么型号的35毫米电影摄影机
all you needed was any 35mm motion picture camera,
和一卷胶片
and a single roll of film.
经过冲洗，就能立刻得到彩色影像
which, when processed, would give an immediate color image.
虽然ECN的画面饱和度较低，色调比特艺彩色更柔和
Although the look of ECN was less saturated and more muted than Technicolor,
但彩色负片的便捷性，人体工程学和经济性最终胜出
the ease, ergonomics, and economics of color negative film ultimately won out,
留下了特艺彩色以及那批饱满，浓郁，充满愉悦的美丽影片，成为永恒的经典
leaving behind Technicolor and its beautiful collection of saturated, rich, joyful films.
感谢大家对本频道的支持
Thanks to everyone for supporting the channel,
特别是Patreon上的朋友们，是你们让频道得以持续
especially those on Patreon who keep the channel going.
那么，下次再见，感谢收看，再会
Otherwise, until next time, thanks for watching and goodbye.